[音乐]
如果你是一只螳螂
If you were a preying mantis, it would be socially acceptable to devour your mate.
，吃掉你的伴侣是社会可以接受的
，如果你是一只蜜獾，你不
And if you're a honey badger, you have no regard for other animals.
关心其他动物
You don't care.
If you're a panda with twins, it's normal to abandon one to take care of the other.
如果你是一只有双胞胎的熊猫，
抛弃其中一只去照顾另一只,
If you're a panda with twins, it's normal to abandon one to take care of the other.
是正常不过的事
But if humans do any of these things, we would call it "wrong", "unfair" or "unjust".
但如果人类做了这些事情中的任何一件，
我们会称其为错误的，不公平或
But if humans do any of these things, we would call it "wrong", "unfair" or "unjust".
不公正
Yeah, why is that?
为什么会如此呢?
Why do humans care so much about justice?
为什么人类对公义如此的在乎?
The Bible has a fascinating response to that question.
圣经对这个问题有一个极好地回答
On page 1, humans are set apart from all other creatures as "the image of God".
在圣经的一开始, 人类在其他受造物中被分别出来, 成为"神的形像"
Yeah, God's representatives who rule the world by his definition of good and evil.
作为神的代表, 以神对善恶的定义来治理世界
This identity is the bedrock of the Bible's view of justice.
这个身份是圣经对于公义的观点的基石
All humans are equal before God and have the right to be treated with dignity and fairness, no matter who you are.
全人类在神的面前是一样的,
有权利以尊严和公平的方式被对待, 不论你是谁
All humans are equal before God and have the right to be treated with dignity and fairness, no matter who you are.
全人类在神的面前是一样的,
有权利以尊严和公平的方式被对待, 不论你是谁
All humans are equal before God and have the right to be treated with dignity and fairness, no matter who you are.
全人类在神的面前是一样的,
有权利以尊严和公平的方式被对待, 不论你是谁
All humans are equal before God and have the right to be treated with dignity and fairness, no matter who you are.
全人类在神的面前是一样的,
有权利以尊严和公平的方式被对待, 不论你是谁是誰
That would be nice, if we all did that. But, we know how the world really works.
如果我们所有人这么做会很好,但我们都知道真实世界是怎样的一回事
The Bible addresses that too.
圣经也讨论这个议题
It shows how we are constantly redefining good and evil to our own advantage at the expense of others.
它显示我们如何一直重新定义善恶, 为的是从对别人的损害中得到自己的好处
Yeah, self preservation.
是的，自我保护。
The weaker someone is, the easier it is to take advantage of them.
一个人越弱小，别人越容易占他便宜
So, in the biblical story, we see this happening on a personal level,
所以,在圣经的故事中, 我们看见这个在个人层面中发生
but also in families and then in communities
也在家庭和社会层面上发生
and in whole civilizations that create injustice, especially towards the vulnerable.
在所有文明中发生, 引致了不公义的出現, 特別是对于弱势的人
But the story doesn't end there.
但故事不只如此
Out of this whole mess, God chose a man named Abraham to start a new kind of family.
在这片混乱的境况中, 神拣选了一个叫亚伯拉罕的人, 去建立一個新形式的家庭
Specifically, Abraham was to teach his family to keep the way of the Lord by doing righteousness and justice.
特別是, 亚伯拉罕要教导他的家庭，透过行出公义, 坚守主的道路,
Doing righteousness, that's a Bible word I don't really use.
"行义", 那其实是个我不太用的圣经字汇
But, what comes to mind is being a good person.
但是, 在我脑海中浮现的是"作个好人"
What does that even mean, "being good"?
"作个好人"到底是指什么?
The biblical Hebrew word for righteousness is "tsedeka".
"公正"在圣经希伯来文中是
It's more specific.
更具体地说，
It's an ethical standard that refers to right relationships between people.
这是个道德标准, 指人与人之间正确的关系
It's about treating others as the image of God.
那是在于把人看作神的形象来对待于
With the God-given dignity they deserve.
给他们应得的神所给予的尊重
This word "justice" is the Hebrew word "mishpat".
他们应得的上帝赋予的尊严和
而"正义"在希伯来文中是"misphat
This word "justice" is the Hebrew word "mishpat".
It can refer to retributive justice.
这可以指报应式的正义
Like if I steal something, I pay the consequences.
像如果我偷了些东西, 我要付出后果
Exactly.
就是这样
Yet, most often in the Bible, mishpat refers to restorative justice.
但是, 在圣经中, mishpat大多是指着修复式的公义
It means going a step further,
这意味着更进一步，
actually seeking out vulnerable people who are being taken advantage of and helping them.
指的是寻找被占便宜的弱势族群, 帮助他们
Yeah, some people call this "charity."
是的, 有人把这称作"慈善事业"
But mishpat involves way more.
但misphat意味着更多
It means taking steps to advocate for the vulnerable and changing social structures to prevent injustice.
这代表站出来去支持弱势族群并改变社会的结构, 以避免不公义的出现
So, justice and righteousness are about a radical, selfless way of life.
所以, 公平和正义是指一种激进的、无私的生活方式
Yeah. You find this idea all over the Bible.
是的, 你在整本圣经中都会看见这个概念
Like here, in the book of Proverbs.
在箴言书中，
What does it mean to "bring about just righteousness"?
"按公义判断"是什么意思?
Open your mouth for those who can't speak for themselves...
"你当为哑巴开口，为一切孤独的伸冤"
And, what do these words mean for the prophets, like Jeremiah?
而这些字对耶利米这样的先知来说, 有什么意义?
Rescue the disadvantaged, and don't tolerate oppression or violence against the immigrant, the orphan and the widow.
"拯救被抢夺的脱离欺压人的手,
不可亏负寄居的和孤儿寡妇, 不可以强暴待他们"
Rescue the disadvantaged, and don't tolerate oppression or violence against the immigrant, the orphan and the widow.
"拯救被抢夺的脱离欺压人的手,
不可亏负寄居的和孤儿寡妇, 不可以强暴待他们"
Rescue the disadvantaged, and don't tolerate oppression or violence against the immigrant, the orphan and the widow.
"拯救被抢夺的脱离欺压人的手,
不可亏负寄居的和孤儿寡妇, 不可以强暴待他们"
Rescue the disadvantaged, and don't tolerate oppression or violence against the immigrant, the orphan and the widow.
"拯救被抢夺的脱离欺压人的手,
不可亏负寄居的和孤儿寡妇, 不可以强暴待他们"
And like here, in the book of Psalms:
还有这里, 诗篇中说道：
"The Lord God upholds justice for the oppressed, gives food to the hungry. and sets the prisoner free.
"他为受屈的伸冤，赐食物与饥饿的。耶和华释放被囚的"
But he thwarts the way of the wicked."
却使恶人的道路弯曲。
Whoa, he thwarts the wicked?
祂使恶人的道路弯曲?
Yeah, in Hebrew the word "wicked" is "rashah".
是的, 恶人一字在希伯来文中是"rashah"
It means "guilty" or "in the wrong".
意思是"有罪的"和"在错误中的"
It refers to someone who mistreats another human, ignoring their dignity as an image of God.
这是指，错误对待他人的人, 他们无视别人作为神的形象的尊严
So justice and righteousness is a big deal to God?
所以正义和公平对神来说是一件很重要的事?
Yes, it is what Abraham's family, the Israelites, were to be all about.
是的, 那就是亚伯拉罕的家庭, 以色列人，要做的所有事
They ended up as immigrant slaves being oppressed unjustly in Egypt.
他们最后成了寄居的奴隶, 在埃及中被不公平地欺压
So God confronted Egypt's evil, declaring them to be "rashah", guilty of injustice.
所以神对抗埃及的邪恶, 称埃及作"rashah", 不公义的罪
So he rescued Israel.
所以祂拯救以色列
But the tragic irony of the Old Testament story is that
但旧约故事讽刺的悲剧是
these redeemed people went on to commit the same acts of injustice against the vulnerable.
这些蒙救赎的人对弱势的人作了同样不公义的行动
So God sent prophets who declared Israel guilty.
所以神差遣先知去宣告以色列有罪
But they weren't the only ones.
但不只他们
There is injustice everywhere.
各处都有不公义
Yeah, some people actively perpetrate injustice.
是的, 有些人积极地作不公义的事
Others receive benefits or privileges from unjust social structures they take for granted.
其他人从他们把不公义的社会结构视为理所当然, 从中获取好处或特权
Sadly, history has shown that when the oppressed gain power, they often become oppressors themselves.
不幸地, 历史显示出当被欺压的人获取权力, 他们经常也成了欺压者
So, we all participate in injustice, actively or passively, even unintentionally.
所以, 我们全都参与在不公义中, 主动或被动, 甚至就在无意之间
We're all the guilty ones.
我们都是有罪的人
So this is the surprising message of the biblical story.
所以这是圣经故事中令人惊讶的信息
God's response to humanity's legacy of injustice is to give us a gift:
神对人类不公义的遗产的回应，是给我们一份礼物:
神对人类不公义的遗产的回应，是给我们一份礼物
the life of Jesus.
耶稣的生命
He did righteousness and justice and yet he died on behalf of the guilty.
他行事正直公义, 却替有罪的人死
But then God declared Jesus to be the righteous one when he rose from the dead.
接着, 当耶稣从死复活时神宣告他是义人
So now, Jesus offers his life to the guilty
，所以现在耶稣将他的生命
所以, 耶稣把他的生命给予了有罪的人
so that they, too, can be declared righteous before God,
所以他们也可在神面前被宣告为义人
not because of anything they have done, but because of what Jesus did for them.
不是因为他们所做的任何事, 而是因耶稣为他们所做的事
The earliest followers of Jesus experienced this righteousness from God not just as a new status,
耶稣最早的跟随者体验到这从神而来的义时, 不只是经历一种新的状态
but as a power that changed their lives and compelled them to act in surprising new ways.
而是一种改变他们生命，并驱使他们以惊人的新方式去行事的能力
Yeah, if God declared someone righteous when they didn't deserve it,
是的, 当神在人不配时,宣称这人为义人
唯一合理的回应, 是去为其他人寻求正直和公义
the only reasonable response is to go and seek righteousness and justice for others.
This is a radical way of life.
他人的我们和正义 这是一种激进的生活方式
It's not always convenient, or easy.
这种生活方式不总是方便，或容易
It is courageously making other people's problems my problems.
而是勇敢地让别人的问题成为我们的问题
This is what Jesus meant by loving your neighbor as yourself.
这就是耶稣说的爱邻如己
It is about a lifetime commitment fueled by the words of the ancient prophet Micah,
这是个关乎一生的承诺, 古时的先知弥迦曾强调这点
God has told you, humans, what is good and what the Lord requires of you.
世人哪, 耶和华已指示你何为善。他向你所要的是什么呢？
It is to do justice,
只要你行公义，
to love mercy
好怜悯
and to walk humbly with your God.
存谦卑的心，与你的神同行。